<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="miscellaneous">

  <title>Miscellaneous Fun</title>

  <introduction>
    <p>In this chapter, I write about various mathematical topics that tickle my fancy. Beware of shenanigans! </p>
  </introduction>

  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!-- Calculus in Incremental Game Mechanics -->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->

  <section xml-id="miscellaneous-incremental">
    <title>Calculus in Incremental Game Mechanics</title>

    <introduction>
      <p><em>December 12th, 2021</em></p>

      <p><em>Incremental games</em>, perhaps better known under the misnomer <em>idle games</em>, are video games whose gameplay centers on the acquisition of in-game currency.</p>

      <p>Roughly speaking, the player spends in-game currencies to increase the rate at which they generate said currencies, which the player then uses to further increase the rate at which they generate said currencies.</p>

      <p>...which they then use to further increase the rate at which they generate said currencies.</p>

      <p>Though not the first game in the genre, the popularity of Orteil's <em>Cookie Clicker</em> in 2013 led to a surge of interest in incremental games, particularly on the flash game site <em>Kongregate</em>. Notable incremental games released since then include <em>Adventure Capitalist</em>, <em>Realm Grinder</em>, and <em>Antimatter Dimensions</em>, among others.</p>

      <p>The history of incremental games is largely beyond the scope of this reading — we're here to do math, not ramble about <em>Cookie Clicker</em>. In this section, we'll take a look at two applications of calculus in incremental games:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Optimizing Happiness in <em>Kittens Game</em>, and</li>
        <li>Modeling Replicanti Growth in <em>Antimatter Dimensions.</em></li>
      </ol>

      <p>The relevant gameplay mechanics in these examples will be explained, so it is by no means necessary to have previously played either of these games. They are, however, very entertaining, and so I highly recommend anyone to go give them a try.</p>
    </introduction>

    <!-- Happiness in Kittens Game -->
    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-incremental-happiness">
      <title>Optimizing Happiness in <em>Kittens Game</em></title>

      <p>Since its release in 2014, <em>Kittens Game</em>,developed by bloodrizer, has gone on to become a cult classic among works in the genre. In <em>Kittens Game</em>, the player is tasked with managing a village of kittens.</p>

      <p>One mechanic in <em>Kittens Game</em> is the management of happiness. Every kitten in the village shares the same happiness value, which is expressed as a percentage.</p>

      <p>Relative to a kitten at 100% happiness, a kitten whose happiness is 50% is only half as productive. Contrast this with a kitten at 120% happiness, who is 120% as productive, somehow. Assuming the player wishes to maximize productivity, it is evident that low happiness is detrimental.</p>

      <p>There are many factors which influence the happiness of the player's kittens, but the main one we will focus on is the mechanic wherein <em>every</em> kitten's happiness goes down by 2% for each kitten 'in excess of 5'. Kittens don't like overpopulation!</p>

      <p>For example, in a village of 6 kittens, each kitten will have a happiness of 98%. This is because the population is 1 greater than the pre-determined threshold of 5. Increasing the population to 16 will decrease every kitten's happiness to 78%.</p>

      <p>Mathematically, this as interpreted as <m>h = 1 - 0.02(p - 5)</m><fn>I'm looking at the behaviour of this function for populations over 5. In the game, the happiness stays at 100% for populations less than 5 kittens.</fn>, where <m>h</m> is the quantity denoting each kitten's happiness, and where <m>p</m> represents the population.</p>

      <p>The happiness of the entire village is consequently <me>h_{total} = p * h = p * (1 - 0.02(p - 5))</me>.</p>

      <p>Those looking to maximize production will therefore wonder: <em>What village population is the most productive?</em> A village with a low population will lack enough kittens to do anything, but a village with too high a population will get nothing done.</p>

      <p>We can feasibly imagine that there is a 'sweet spot' somewhere in the middle, with regard to the population. Let's now go about finding it. First, let <m>h_{total}</m> be notated as a function of <m>p</m>:<me>h_{total}(p) = p * h = p * (1 - 0.02(p - 5)) = 1.1p - 0.02p^2</me>.</p>

      <p>Since this is a quadratic function, we <em>could</em> complete the square to rewrite <m>h_{total}(p)</m> in vertex form, but instead, let's find the maximum using calculus. We'll employ the first derivative to find stationary points, and the second derivative to verify extrema.<fn>Since the function is polynomial, it follows that we can differentiate as much as we want.</fn></p>

      <p>A little bit of differentiation:
        <md>
          <mrow>            \amp h_{total}(p) = 1.1p - 0.02p^2</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies \; \amp h'_{total}(p) = 1.1 - 0.04p</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies \; \amp h''_{total}(p) = -0.04</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>If we solve for <m>h'_{total}(p) = 0</m>, we see that <m>p = \frac{1.1}{0.04} = 27.5</m>. For this value of <m>p</m> (actually, for all values of <m>p</m>), the second derivative is negative, so there is definitely a local maximum at <m>p = 27.5</m>.</p>

      <p>We can't exactly have half of a kitten (at least, not without raising serious ethical concerns), so this means that either 27 or 28 kittens is the optimal population for the player's village.</p>

      <p>Alternatively, we know from pre-calculus that the vertex of a parabola is located at <m>p = \frac{b}{2a}</m>, so we could've eschewed the use of calculus by simply calculating <m>p = \frac{1.1}{2 * 0.02} = 27.5</m>.</p>

      <p>To round off this section, let's consider a different mechanic. Luxury items are another factor which affects kitten happiness — for each luxury item in stock, the happiness of every kitten increases by a flat 10%. What effect would these items have on the value of the 'sweet spot'? I'll let you ruminate on that...</p>
    </subsection>

    <!-- Replicanti in Antimatter Dimensions -->
    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-incremental-replicanti">
      <title>Modeling Replicanti Growth in <em>Antimatter Dimensions</em></title>

      <p>In <em>Antimatter Dimensions</em>, developed by Hevipelle, the player's goal is to produce antimatter. Antimatter is produced by the titular Antimatter Dimensions, whose efficiency can be increased through the purchase of Infinity Dimensions (it's quite complicated, so don't worry about it).</p>

      <p>Replicanti are a mechanic that further increases antimatter production. When an in-game tick elapses, every replicanti has a chance to replicate. The duration of an in-game tick, as well as the chance of replication, can be improved with upgrades. Simply put, more replicanti leads to more antimatter.</p>

      <p>Let <m>r(i)</m> be the function expressing the amount of replicanti present at a time <m>i</m> in ticks, and let <m>i(t)</m> be the function representing the number of in-game ticks elapsed at this same time <m>t</m>, but now in seconds. Suppose the constants <m>p</m> and <m>d</m> represent the probability of replication and the duration of an in-game tick, respectively.<fn>Note that we've moved on to a different example, so the notation no longer represents what it did previously.</fn></p>

      <p>Our goal is to find an equation for <m>r(i)</m> which accurately models the growth of replicanti. To find said equation, let's approach the problem by taking a look at its derivative, <m>\frac{dr}{di}(i)</m>.</p>

      <p>We know that the rate at which replicanti grow is proportional to the amount of replicanti already present: <me>\frac{dr}{di}(i) = p * r(i)</me>.</p>

      <p>This is, in fact, a differential equation. In fact, it's one of the simplest examples of a differential equation — you may already know what the answer is. Let's multiply both sides by <m>di</m>: <me>dr = p * r(i) \; di</me>.</p>

      <p>Divide both sides by <m>r(i)</m>: <me>\frac{1}{r(i)} \; dr = p \; di</me>.</p>

      <p>Integrate both sides: <me>\int \frac{1}{r(i)} \; dr = \int p \; di</me>.</p>

      <p>Almost there: <me>ln|r(i)| = pi + c</me>.</p>

      <p>And finally, <me>r(i) = Ce^{pi}</me>. There <em>is</em> one caveat, however. We wanted <m>r(t)</m>, not <m>r(i)</m>. Luckily, <m>i</m> and <m>t</m> are closely related through the function <m>i(t)</m>, so our function should actually resemble the following: <me>r(t) = Ce^{pi(t)}</me>.</p>

      <p>As it turns out, <m>i(t) = \frac{t}{d}</m>. For example, if <m>t = 10</m> seconds and <m>d = 0.5 </m> seconds, <m>i(t)</m> would assume a value of <m>\frac{10}{0.5} = 20</m> ticks.</p>

      <p>Therefore, we arrive at a final equation for <m>r(t)</m>: <me>r(t) = Ce^{\frac{p}{d}t}</me>. I bet it's not every day that video games make you think of calculus!</p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!-- How to Make Any Graph Spin in Desmos -->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->

  <section xml-id="miscellaneous-spin">
    <title>How to Make Any Graph Spin in Desmos</title>

    <introduction>
      <p><em>January 9th, 2022</em></p>

      <p>Today, we're gonna mess around in Desmos. That's right, I'll show you how to make any Desmos graph rotate around any location on the plane you want! Fair warning, what's about to unfold is a bit ridiculous.</p>

      <p>The approach we'll take has three main steps, as follows:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p>Parameterize the curve into two functions, <m>x(t)</m> and <m>y(t)</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Apply the rotation matrix, <m>\begin{bmatrix} cos(\theta) &amp; -sin(\theta) \\ sin(\theta) &amp; \text{ }cos(\theta) \end{bmatrix}</m> to the column vector <m>\begin{bmatrix} x(t) \\ y(t) \end{bmatrix}</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Create a slider for <m>\theta</m> and let the value of <m>\theta</m> vary over time.</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>The first step is usually the hardest.</p>
    </introduction>

    <!-- Parameterize the graph -->
    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-spin-parameterization">
      <title><em>Erster Ablauf:</em> Parameterize the Graph</title>

      <p>To be completely transparent with you, this post is going to be very hand-wavy. I'll show you exactly what you need to do to get your graph rotating, with little further explanation. I really recommend you look deeper into the topics we're going to look at, though. There's a lot of cool stuff here!</p>

      <p>So, let's get started by parameterizing our curve. It'll be good to work with an example, so throughout this post, I'll be making the implicitly-defined curve <m>y^3 + 3xy = 2</m> spin.</p>

      <p>The process follows these steps:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p>Solve either for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>, or for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>If you solved for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>, let <m>x_{c}(t)</m> equal your expression for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>t</m>, and let <m>y_{c}(t) = t</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>If you solved for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>, let <m>x_{c}(t) = t</m>, and let <m>y_{c}(t)</m> equal your expression for <m>y</m> in terms of <m>t</m>.</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>On the other hand, if your curve is already parameterized, then you can skip this whole first section. Convenient!</p>

      <p>Now, for the curve <m>y^3 + 3xy = 2</m>, it'll be easier to solve for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>, so let's do that: <me> y^3 + 3xy = 2 \implies x = \frac{2 - y^3}{3y}</me>.</p>

      <p>Then we let <m>x_{c}(t) = \frac{2 - t^3}{3t}</m> and <m>y_{c}(t) = t</m>. That's it, our curve is now parameterized! Let's go look at the fruits of our labour in Desmos.</p>

      <image source="image/miscellaneous-spin_1.png" width="100%"/>

      <p>Type what you see in the image above into a new Desmos graph. <em>If the picture is blurry, try zooming in on your browser or opening the image in a new tab</em>. You should get two identical curves, right on top of each other. It's important to set a large range for the parameterization variable <m>t</m> in order to draw the curve.</p>

      <p>Try messing around with that inequality for <m>t</m> and see what happens.</p>

      <p>With some overly complex curves, simply solving for one variable in terms of the other is not going to work. In that case, you'll have to apply more complicated parameterization techniques — check online! You could also just break the curve up into parts, and spin each part separately.</p>
    </subsection>

    <!-- Apply rotation matrix -->
    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-spin-matrices">
      <title><em>Zweiter Ablauf:</em> Apply the Transformation Matrix</title>

      <p>What the line <m>(x_{c}(t), y_{c}(t))</m> does in Desmos is graph all the points <m>(x, y)</m> on the plane which satisfy the equations <m>x = x_{c}(t)</m> and <m>y = y_{c}(t)</m> as <m>t</m> varies between its lower and upper bound. Unsurprisingly, that traces out the curve in question.</p>

      <p>So now, let's add in the rotation! Doing so is going to require us to venture to the land of linear algebra, as we're going to utilize some matrices. You don't need to know any linear algebra to follow the process, though some of the explanations may fly over your head. That's no problem.</p>

      <p>We can express any point <m>(x, y)</m> in the x-y plane as a 2 by 1 column vector, <m>\begin{bmatrix} x \\ y \end{bmatrix}</m>.</p>

      <p>If we then wish to rotate the point <m>(x, y)</m> around the origin by an angle <m>a</m> to obtain the rotated point <m>(x_{r}, y_{r})</m>, we need to multiply the column vector with the 2D rotation matrix on the left, like so: <me>(x_{r}, y_{r}) = \begin{bmatrix} cos(a) &amp; -sin(a) \\ sin(a) &amp; \text{ }cos(a) \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} x \\ y \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} x_{r} \\ y_{r} \end{bmatrix}</me>.</p>

      <p>In our case, we're going to multiply using the column vector <m>\begin{bmatrix} x_{c}(t) \\ y_{c}(t) \end{bmatrix}</m>, which represents our curve. A bit of matrix multiplication gives the following: <me> (x_{cr}(t), y_{cr}(t)) = \begin{bmatrix} cos(a) &amp; -sin(a) \\ sin(a) &amp; \text{ }cos(a) \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} x_{c}(t) \\ y_{c}(t) \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} x_{c}(t)\cos(a) - y_{c}(t)\sin(a) \\ x_{c}(t)\sin(a) + y_{c}(t)\cos(a) \end{bmatrix}</me>.</p>

      <p>If we now compare components, we see that <m>x_{cr}(t) = x_{c}(t)\cos(a) - y_{c}(t)\sin(a)</m> and <m>y_{cr}(t) = x_{c}(t)\sin(a) + y_{c}(t)\cos(a)</m>.</p>

      <image source="image/miscellaneous-spin_2.png" width="100%"/>

      <p>Add these new lines of math to your Desmos graph. You should see a copy of the curve, and if you press play on <m>a</m>, the graph should start rotating! What a success, right? By the way, my graph is in radians.</p>

      <p>As <m>a</m> increases, the graph rotates counterclockwise. As <m>a</m> decreases, the graph rotates clockwise.</p>
    </subsection>

    <!-- Extra steps for rotation around a certain point -->
    <!-- Rotation matrices rotate around the origin, so we displace the original graph by (-x_r, -y_r), which moves the point of rotation (x_r, y_r) to the origin, then add back (x_r, y_r) after applying the rotation matrix -->
    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-spin-point">
      <title><em>Dritter Ablauf:</em> Rotate Around a Specified Point</title>

      <p>Perhaps you require the curve to rotate around a certain point. No problem, this can also be done! Given a point of rotation <m>(x_0, y_0)</m>, we execute another step-oriented process:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p>Translate the graph of <m>(x_{c}(t), y_{c}(t))</m> by <m>-x_0</m> units on the <m>x</m>-axis and by <m>-y_0</m> units on the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>
        <li><p>Apply the transformation matrix to the translated column vector.</p></li>
        <li><p>Translate the resulting graph of <m>(x_{cr}(t), y_{cr}(t))</m> by <m>x_0</m> units on the <m>x</m>-axis and by <m>y_0</m> units on the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>What this process does is it moves the point of rotation from <m>(x_0, y_0)</m> to the origin, applies the rotation matrix, then moves the point of rotation from the origin back to <m>(x_0, y_0)</m>.</p>

      <p>These steps must be undertaken in this order, as the rotation matrix only rotates around the origin. This is what's going on, mathematically: 
        <md>
          <mrow>(x_{cr}(t), y_{cr}(t)) \amp = \begin{bmatrix} cos(a) &amp; -sin(a) \\ sin(a) &amp; \text{ }cos(a) \end{bmatrix} \left( \begin{bmatrix} x_{c}(t) \\ y_{c}(t) \end{bmatrix} - \begin{bmatrix} x_0 \\ y_0 \end{bmatrix} \right) + \begin{bmatrix} x_0 \\ y_0 \end{bmatrix}</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \begin{bmatrix} (x_{c}(t) - x_0)\cos(a) - (y_{c}(t) - y_0)\sin(a) + x_0 \\ (x_{c}(t)- x_0)\sin(a) + (y_{c}(t) - y_0)\cos(a) + y_0 \end{bmatrix}.</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <image source="image/miscellaneous-spin_3.png" width="100%"/>

      <p>Add what you see in the image to your Desmos graph. The red graph rotates around the Point of Rotation! You can, of course, change the values of <m>x_0</m> and <m>y_0</m> to your heart's content, as well as the rate of rotation, etc.</p>

      <p>I've created an example Desmos project for you to fiddle around with. Click <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/a5glisxpi6/">here</url>.</p>

      <p>There are, of course, other methods to rotate a curve in Desmos, and I hope you find this approach relatively simple. Now, go forth and make your graphs spin!</p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!-- C x R: A Short Thought Experiment -->
  <!---->
  <!---->
  <!---->

  <section xml-id="miscellaneous-ctimesr">
    <title><m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m>: A Short Thought Experiment</title>

    <introduction>
      <p><em>January 20th, 2022</em></p>

      <p>Do you like <m>\mathbb{C}</m>? And do you like <m>\mathbb{R}</m>? If your answer to both those questions is 'yes', then <em>obviously</em>, the logical thing to consider afterwards is the holy matrimony of <m>\mathbb{C}</m> and <m>\mathbb{R}</m>.</p>

      <p>Now presenting to you... <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m>. Let's get to know our new married couple. </p>

      <p>A sensible first question to ask is "what exactly is the set <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> comprised of"? Well, following the definition of the Cartesian product, we see that<me>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R} = \{ (a, b) \: | \: a \in \mathbb{C} \land b \in \mathbb{R} \}</me>. An example of an element in <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> is <m>(1 + 5i, \: 4)</m>. I'm sure you'll agree with me that <m>1 + 5i \in \mathbb{C}</m> and <m>4 \in \mathbb{R}</m>. So then, the contents of this blog post are dedicated to considering some interesting properties of this unusual set.</p>

      <p>A basic understanding of the following concepts on the part of the reader would go a long way: <em>complex numbers, set theory, fields, cardinalities of infinite sets, bijective maps, proofs of injectivity and surjectivity</em>.</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-ctimesr-field">
      <title>An Attempt to Define <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> as a Field</title>

      <p>In mathematics, we define a field to be a set <m>S</m> on which the binary operations of addition and multiplication are defined, with the additional requirement that the following list of properties hold:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p><m>a + b \in S</m> and <m>a \cdot b \in S</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>a + (b + c) = (a + b) + c</m> and <m>a \cdot (b \cdot c) = (a \cdot b) \cdot c</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>a + b = b + a</m> and <m>a \cdot b = b \cdot a</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>a \cdot (b + c) = (a \cdot b) + (a \cdot c)</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>\exists e_{add} \in S \: | \: a + e_{add} = a</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>\exists e_{mul} \in S \: | \: a \cdot e_{mul} = a</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>\forall a \in S, \exists -a \in S \: | \: a + (-a) = e_{add}</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>\forall a \neq 0 \in S, \exists a^{-1} \in S \: | \: a \cdot a^{-1} = e_{mul}</m>,</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>where <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are any elements of <m>S</m>. In this context, <m>e_{add}</m> is known as the additive identity and <m>e_{mul}</m> is known as the multiplicative identity.</p>

      <p>We now wish to define addition and multiplication on our set <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> in a way that satisfies all the properties of a field. There are a lot of potential starting options, but I would like to propose what I think is the most natural approach.</p>

      <p>Before that, though, here's some more notation. Let<me>a = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \qquad b = (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b) \qquad c = (x_c + iy_c, \: z_c)</me>be three arbitrary elements of <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m>, with <m>x_{abc}, \: y_{abc}, \: z_{abc} \in \mathbb{R}</m><fn>Please note that, in this context, <m>z</m> refers strictly to <em>real</em> numbers!</fn>. We now define addition and multiplication in the following manner:
        <md>
          <mrow>a + b = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) + (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b) = (x_a + x_b + i(y_a + y_b), \: z_a + z_b)</mrow>
          <mrow>a \cdot b = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b) = (x_a x_b - y_a y_b + i(x_a y_b + x_b y_a), \: z_a z_b).</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>I think this is a fairly pragmatic way of going about the matter, as we are simply adding and multiplying the complex and real components of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> separately.</p>

      <p>The rest of this subsection is used to prove that this particular definition of addition and multiplication satisfy the aforementioned properties of a field.</p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>1. <m>a + b \in S</m> and <m>a \cdot b \in S</m>. <em>The set</em> <m>S</m> <em>is closed under addition and multiplication</em>. Per our definition of addition, <m>a + b = (x_a + x_b + i(y_a + y_b), \: z_a + z_b)</m>. Since <m>x_a + x_b + i(y_a + y_b) \in \mathbb{C}</m> and <m>z_a + z_b \in \mathbb{R}</m>, it follows that <m>a + b \in S</m>. A similar argument shows that <m>a \cdot b \in S</m>.</p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>2. <m>a + (b + c) = (a + b) + c</m> and <m>a \cdot (b \cdot c) = (a \cdot b) \cdot c</m>. <em>Addition and multiplication are associative</em>. Observe that
        <md>
          <mrow>a + (b + c) \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) + (x_b + x_c + i(y_b + y_c), \: z_b + z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a + x_b + x_c + i(y_a + y_b + y_c), \: z_a + z_b + z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a + x_b + i(y_a + y_b), \: z_a + z_b) + (x_c + iy_c, \: z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (a + b) + c.</mrow>
        </md>
      and
        <md>
          <mrow>a \cdot (b \cdot c) \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_b x_c - y_b y_c + i(x_b y_c + x_c y_b), \: z_b z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a x_b x_c - x_a y_b y_c - y_a x_b y_c - y_a y_b x_c + i(x_a x_b y_c + x_a y_b x_c + y_a x_b x_c - y_a y_b y_c), \: z_a z_b z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a x_b - y_a y_b + i(x_a y_b + x_b y_a), \: z_a z_b) \cdot (x_c + iy_c, \: z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (a \cdot b) \cdot c.</mrow>
        </md>
      Therefore addition and multiplication are associative<fn>On an unrelated side note, I think I'm going to go blind.</fn>.
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>3. <m>a + b = b + a</m> and <m>a \cdot b = b \cdot a</m>. <em>Addition and multiplication are commutative</em>. Observe that
        <md>
          <mrow>a + b \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) + (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a + x_b + i(y_a + y_b), \: z_a + z_b)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_b + x_a + i(y_b + y_a), \: z_b + z_a)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b) + (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = b + a.</mrow>
        </md>
      and
        <md>
          <mrow>a \cdot b \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a x_b - y_a y_b + i(x_a y_b + x_b y_a), \: z_a z_b)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_b x_a - y_b y_a + i(x_b y_a + x_a y_b), \: z_b z_a)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b) \cdot (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = b \cdot a.</mrow>
        </md>
      Therefore addition and multiplication are commutative.
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>4. <m>a \cdot (b + c) = (a \cdot b) + (a \cdot c)</m>. <em>Multiplication is distributive over addition.</em> We have
        <md>
          <mrow>a \cdot (b + c) \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_b + x_c + i(y_b + y_c), \: z_b + z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a x_b + x_a x_c - y_a y_b - y_a y_c + ix_a y_b + ix_a y_c + iy_a x_b + iy_a x_c, \: z_a z_b + z_a z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = ((x_a x_b - y_a y_b + i(x_a y_b + y_a x_b)) + (x_a x_c - y_a y_c + i(x_a y_c + y_a x_c)), \: z_a z_b + z_a z_c)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (a \cdot b) + (a \cdot c).</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>5. <m>\exists e_{add} \in S \: | \: a + e_{add} = a</m>. <em>There exists an additive identity</em> <m>e_{add}</m> <em>such that for every element</em> <m>a</m> <em>in</em> <m>S</m> <em>,</em> <m>a + e_{add} = a</m>. Let <m>e_{add} = (0 + 0i, \: 0)</m>. Then<me>a + e_{add} = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) + (0 + 0i, \: 0) = (x_a + 0 + i(y_a + 0), \: z_a + 0) = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) = a.</me>
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>6. <m>\exists e_{mul} \in S \: | \: a \cdot e_{mul} = a</m>. <em>There exists a multiplicative identity</em> <m>e_{mul}</m> <em>such that for every element</em> <m>a</m> <em>in</em> <m>S</m> <em>,</em> <m>a \cdot e_{mul} = a</m>. Let <m>e_{mul} = (1 + 0i, \: 1)</m>. Then<me>a \cdot e_{mul} = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (1 + 0i, \: 1) = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) = a.</me>
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>7. <m>\forall a \in S, \exists -a \in S \: | \: a + (-a) = e_{add}</m>. <em>Every element</em> <m>a</m> <em>in</em> <m>S</m> <em>has an additive inverse</em> <m>-a</m> <em>such that</em> <m>a + (-a) = e_{add}</m>. Let <m>-a = (-x_a - iy_a, \: -z_a)</m>. Then
        <md>
          <mrow>a + (-a) \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) + (-x_a - iy_a, \: -z_a)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (x_a - x_a + i(y_a - y_a), \: z_a - z_a) </mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = (0 + 0i, \: 0)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = e_{add}.</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>8. <m>\forall a \neq 0 \in S, \exists a^{-1} \in S \: | \: a \cdot a^{-1} = e_{mul}</m>. <em>Every non-zero element</em> <m>a</m> <em>in</em> <m>S</m> <em>has a multiplicative inverse</em> <m>a^{-1}</m> <em>such that</em> <m>a \cdot a^{-1} = e_{mul}</m>. Let <m>d = a^{-1} = (x_d + iy_d, \: z_d)</m>. We now solve for <m>x_d</m>, <m>y_d</m>, and <m>z_d</m> in terms of <m>x_a</m>, <m>y_a</m>, and <m>z_a</m>. Observe that
        <md>
          <mrow>a \cdot d \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_d + iy_d, \: z_d) = (1 + 0i, \: 1)</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies (1 + 0i, \: 1) \amp = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a) \cdot (x_d + iy_d, \: z_d)</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies (1 + 0i, \: 1) \amp = (x_a x_d - y_a y_d + i(x_a y_d + x_d y_a), \: z_a z_d)</mrow>
        </md>
      We then are presented with the following three equations:<me>x_a x_d - y_a y_d = 1, \qquad x_a y_d + x_d y_a = 0, \qquad z_a z_d = 1</me>. The first two equations form a nice system of equations. After some algebra, we see that <me>x_d = \frac{x_a}{x_a^2 + y_a^2}, \qquad y_d = \frac{-y_a}{x_a^2 + y_a^2}, \qquad z_d = \frac{1}{z_a}.</me> Hence, we see that <me>a^{-1} = \left(\frac{x_a}{x_a^2 + y_a^2} - i\frac{y_a}{x_a^2 + y_a^2}, \: \frac{1}{z_a}\right).</me>Unfortunately, this is where tragedy strikes. You may have noticed that all elements of the form <m>(x_a + iy_a, \: 0)</m> lack a multiplicative inverse, as <m>\frac{1}{0}</m> is not defined.
      </p>

      <p>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</p>

      <p>So, this definition of addition and multiplication was very close to satisfying all the properties of a field, but could not fulfill this last requirement. If it's any consolation, we have at least shown that <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> is a commutative ring under these addition and multiplication operations.</p>

      <p>There may exist a definition of addition and multiplication which makes the set <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> into a field, but I am not sure. This is somewhat similar to how <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m> is not a field when multiplication is defined component-wise. Indeed, there seem to be many analogues between the set <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> and <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m>.</p>

      <p>Speaking of which...</p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-ctimesr-cardinality">
      <title>The Cardinality of <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m></title>

      <p>There are obviously an uncountably infinite amount of elements in <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m>, but we can still get a feel for the cardinality of this set, <m>|\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}|</m>. In particular, I claim that <m>|\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}| = |\mathbb{R}|</m>.</p>

      <p>There is more than one way to show that this is true, and we will explore one such method involving bijective maps. By definition, two sets have the same cardinality if there exists a bijection from one set to the other.</p>

      <p>Therefore, finding a bijection from <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> to <m>\mathbb{R}</m> will prove that these two sets share the same cardinality. However, such a task is a little difficult. Instead, we are going to be a little cheeky and make use of a proven fact that <m>|\mathbb{R}^3| = |\mathbb{R}|</m><fn>Refer to <url href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/243590/bijection-from-mathbb-r-to-mathbb-rn">this</url> post for an explanation of this result</fn>.</p>

      <p>So instead, we will find a bijective map <m>f</m>, where <m>f: \mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}^3</m>. The most sensible thing to first try is, in my opinion, the map <m>(x + iy, \: z) \mapsto (x, \: y, \: z)</m>. We now show that <m>f</m> is injective and surjective.</p>

      <p>Let <m>a = (x_a + iy_a, \: z_a)</m> and <m>b = (x_b + iy_b, \: z_b)</m> represent two arbitrary elements in <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m>, and suppose <m>f(a) = f(b)</m>. It then follows that <m>(x_a, y_a, z_a) = (x_b, y_b, z_b)</m> and so we have<me>x_a = x_b \qquad y_a = y_b \qquad z_a = z_b</me>, in which case <m>a = b</m>.</p>

      <p>Next, suppose <m>C = (x_c, y_c, z_c)</m> is an arbitrary element of <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m>. Observe that the element <m>c = (x_c + iy_c, \: z_c)</m> in <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> satisfies <m>f(c) = C</m>.</p>

      <p>Since <m>f</m> is both injective and surjective, it follows that <m>f</m> is bijective and hence <m>|\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}| = |\mathbb{R}^3| = |\mathbb{R}|</m>. If you are unfamiliar with infinite sets, such a result probably seems bizarre, but this is just how infinite sets are.</p>

      <p>Does the set <m>\mathbb{C} \times \mathbb{R}</m> have any practical applications? Maybe. But for now, I think I'll stick to the usual <m>\mathbb{C}</m> and <m>\mathbb{R}</m> we all know and love (?).</p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

  <section xml-id="miscellaneous-three_methods">
    <title>Compare and Contrast: Three Methods for Integrating <m>\sin^6(x)</m></title>

    <introduction>
      <p><em>April 14, 2022</em></p>

      <p>It's been a long time since I've posted, hasn't it? School's been keeping me occupied, and I've also been in a little bit of a creative rut when it comes to ideas for new blog posts. But not for now!</p>

      <p>As the title implies, we will be looking at three techniques for finding the general antiderivative of the function <m>f(x) = \sin^6(x)</m>, which is definitely not the easiest function to integrate. The three methods which we will explore are:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p>Integration by standard trigonometric identities,</p></li>
        <li><p>Integration by trigonometric reduction formulae, and</p></li>
        <li><p>Integration by complex definitions of <m>\sin</m> and <m>\cos</m>.</p></li>
      </ol>

      <p>Mathematical shenanigans are to follow. I was inspired to write up this post after I spoke with a friend about how to integrate the somewhat friendlier function <m>\sin^4(x)</m>.</p>

      <p>Ultimately, I decided to tackle a slightly higher power of <m>\sin</m> in this article to better get my points across.</p>

      <p>I think that's enough preamble for now. Time for some integration! Just in time for my Calc 2 final, as well :)</p>
    </introduction>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-three_methods-standard">
      <title>Evaluating <m>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx</m> by Standard Trigonometric Identities</title>

      <p>In this first technique, our approach will be to repeatedly use variants of the well-known trig identity <me>\cos(2x) = 1 - \sin^2(x)</me> and <me>\cos^2(x) = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{\cos(2x)}{2}</me> to get rid of those pesky exponents.</p>

      <p>First, let us quickly rearrange the first identity to isolate <m>\sin^2(x)</m>: <me>\cos(2x) = 1 - \sin^2(x) \implies \sin^2(x) = \frac{1}{2} - \frac{\cos(2x)}{2}.</me></p>

      <p>The following mathematical work will be a bit sparse on commentary, but hopefully the steps taken are easy enough to follow. The idea is to, for lack of a better word, spam these two identities to gradually wear down the exponents.
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \int (\sin^2(x))^3 \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int \left(\frac{1}{2} - \frac{\cos(2x)}{2}\right)^3 \: dx.</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>In what follows, I am going to make frequent use of the binomial theorem. If you aren't sure what that is, please search it up, or refer to <url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binomial_theorem">this</url> Wikipedia page.</p>

      <p>The primary goal of this article is to discuss integration techniques, and the contents are structured as such.</p>

      <p>Using this theorem, we obtain: 
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \int \left(\frac{1}{2} - \frac{\cos(2x)}{2}\right)^3 \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int \frac{1}{2^3} - 3 \cdot \frac{1}{2^2} \frac{\cos(2x)}{2} + 3 \cdot \frac{1}{2} \frac{\cos^2(2x)}{2^2} - \frac{\cos^3(2x)}{2^3} \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \frac{1}{8} \int 1 \: dx - \frac{3}{8} \int \cos(2x) \: dx + \frac{3}{8} \int \cos^2(2x) \: dx - \frac{1}{8} \int \cos^3(2x) \: dx</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>We have now broken up our starting integral into four, more manageable integrals. For the sake of brevity, we will work through integrating just the rightmost integral, <me>\int \cos^3(2x) \: dx.</me>The other integrals are left as an exercise for the reader (a classic).</p>

      <p>The technique for integrating this above integral is taught in most integral calculus courses, and is as follows:
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \cos^3(2x) \: dx \amp = \int \cos(2x) \cdot \cos^2(2x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int \cos(2x)(1 - \sin^2(2x)) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int \cos(2x) \: dx - \int \sin^2(2x)\cos(2x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \frac{1}{2} \sin(2x) - \frac{1}{6} \sin^3(2x) + C.</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>Returning back to the original integral, we'll piece together the smaller integrals to get the final result.
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \frac{1}{8} \int 1 \: dx - \frac{3}{8} \int \cos(2x) \: dx + \frac{3}{8} \int \cos^2(2x) \: dx - \frac{1}{8} \int \cos^3(2x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \frac{1}{8}x - \frac{3}{16} \sin(2x) + \frac{3}{16}x + \frac{3}{64} \sin(4x) - \frac{1}{16} \sin(2x) + \frac{1}{48} \sin^3(2x) + C</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \frac{5}{16}x - \frac{1}{4} \sin(2x) + \frac{3}{64} \sin(4x) + \frac{1}{48} \sin^3(2x) + C</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>Let us put the final answer on a new line, for posterity's sake: <me>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx = \frac{5}{16}x - \frac{1}{4} \sin(2x) + \frac{3}{64} \sin(4x) + \frac{1}{48} \sin^3(2x) + C.</me> Take note of this expression, as we will be comparing it with other, equivalent<fn>Equivalent, up to a constant of integration.</fn> expressions obtained by different methods.</p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-three_methods-reduction">
      <title>Evaluating <m>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx</m> by Trigonometric Reduction Formulae</title>

      <p>Trig reduction formulae are powerful tools that express integrals of powers of trigonometric functions in terms with lesser powers. The process can be repeated until the remaining integral is simple to evaluate.</p>

      <p>It's like recursion. Sort of.</p>

      <p>The trig reduction formula which we will be using is the standard formula for <m>\sin^n(x)</m>, and takes the following form for any <m>n \in \mathbb{N}, n \geq 2</m>:<me>\int \sin^n(x) \: dx = -\frac{1}{n} \sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{n-1}{n} \int \sin^{n-2}(x) \: dx. </me>I'll quickly go over the derivation of this formula, as it's not <em>too</em> complicated, and is also a practical example of integration by parts.</p>

      <p>We choose <m>u</m> and <m>dv</m> as follows, then proceed.
        <md>
          <mrow>u \amp = \sin^{n-1}(x)</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies du \amp = (n-1)\sin^{n-2}(x)\cos(x)</mrow>
          <mrow></mrow>
          <mrow>dv \amp = \sin(x)</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies v \amp = -\cos(x)</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>Quite a bit of algebra follows, as well as the use of a trigonometric identity.
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^n(x) \: dx \amp = -\sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + \int (n-1)\sin^{n-2}(x)\cos^2(x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + \int (n-1)\sin^{n-2}(x) (1 - \sin^2(x)) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + \int (n-1)\sin^{n-2}(x) \: dx - \int (n-1)\sin^n(x) \: dx</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>Let's bring the constants out of the integrals, and move that rightmost term over to the left.
        <md>
          <mrow>n \int \sin^n(x) \: dx \amp = -\sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + (n-1) \int \sin^{n-2}(x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\implies \int \sin^n(x) \: dx \amp = -\frac{1}{n} \sin^{n-1}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{n-1}{n} \int \sin^{n-2}(x) \: dx.</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>One trig reduction formula, hot off the presses. Of course, our desire is now to shove in <m>n = 6</m> and see where the formula takes us:
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = -\frac{1}{6} \sin^{5}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{5}{6} \int \sin^{4}(x) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\frac{1}{6} \sin^{5}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{5}{6} \left(-\frac{1}{4} \sin^{3}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{3}{4} \int \sin^{2}(x) \: dx \right)</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\frac{1}{6} \sin^{5}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{5}{6} \left(-\frac{1}{4} \sin^{3}(x)\cos(x) + \frac{3}{4} \left( -\frac{1}{2} \sin(x)\cos(x) + \frac{1}{2} \int 1 \: dx \right) \right)</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>After performing quite a bit of multiplication, we get the final answer<me>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx = -\frac{1}{6} \sin^{5}(x)\cos(x) - \frac{1}{24} \sin^{3}(x)\cos(x) - \frac{5}{16} \sin(x)\cos(x) + \frac{5}{16}x + C.</me></p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-three_methods-complex">
      <title>Evaluating <m>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx</m> by Complex Definitions of <m>\sin</m> and <m>\cos</m></title>

      <p>The third and final integration technique covered in this blog post is integration using the complex definitions of <m>\sin</m> and <m>\cos</m>. From what I've noticed, this method is the least well-known of the three, which is a real shame, as it's quite powerful.</p>

      <p>For example, this technique was not covered in my integral calculus class, though it is in an appendix at the back of the course textbook.<fn>An appendix which most students probably did not bother to read.</fn></p>

      <p>My goal is to cover this method of integration with minimal discussion of complex numbers. It turns out that this integration strategy can be employed with <em>very</em> little knowledge of them.</p> 

      <p>In fact, in addition to what we've covered so far, you need only know three more facts:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p><m>\sin(x) = \frac{e^{ix} - e^{-ix}}{2i}</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>\cos(x) = \frac{e^{ix} + e^{-ix}}{2}</m></p></li>
        <li><p><m>i^2 = -1</m>.</p></li>
      </ol> 

      <p>The first two formulae are the so-called complex definitions of <m>\sin</m> and <m>\cos</m>. If you are confused or interested in how they came to be, I highly encourage you to look them up online.</p>

      <p>As for the symbol <m>i</m>, all that is important to know for now is that it has the curious property where its square equals <m>-1</m>.</p>

      <p>The five-step plan of attack for evaluating integrals of the form <m>\int \sin^n(x) \: dx</m> using complex numbers is as follows:</p>

      <ol>
        <li><p>Replace <m>\sin(x)</m> with its complex definition.</p></li>
        <li><p>Split the integrand into two terms.</p></li>
        <li><p>Apply the binomial theorem.</p></li>
        <li><p>Finesse the resulting expression to rewrite it in terms of <m>\sin</m> and/or <m>\cos</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Integrate the new integrand term by term.</p></li>
      </ol> 

      <p>We demonstrate this strategy with the titular integral <m>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx</m>.
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \int \left(\frac{e^{ix} - e^{-ix}}{2i}\right)^6 \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int \frac{1}{(2i)^6} (e^{ix} - e^{-ix})^6 \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int -\frac{1}{2^6} (e^{6ix} - 6e^{4ix} + 15e^{2ix} - 20 + 15e^{-2ix} - 6e^{-4ix} + e^{-6ix}) \: dx</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>By this point, we have finished executing step 3. The step which follows is the most counter-intuitive, in my opinion.</p>

      <p>Essentially, the idea is to group terms of like exponents together, and carefully perturb the integrand to have the formulas for <m>\sin</m> and <m>\cos</m> reappear.<fn>The decision to leave the constant multiplier inside the integral is purely stylistic. Everything works out the same if you opt to bring it out of the integral.</fn>
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \int -\frac{1}{64} (e^{6ix} - 6e^{4ix} + 15e^{2ix} - 20 + 15e^{-2ix} - 6e^{-4ix} + e^{-6ix}) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = \int -\frac{1}{64} \left((e^{6ix} + e^{-6ix}) - 6(e^{4ix} + e^{-4ix}) + 15(e^{2ix} + e^{-2ix}) - 20\right) \: dx</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>Before we move on, convince yourself of two things. First, that equality still holds, after rearranging all those terms, and second, that <m>\cos(nx) = \frac{e^{nix} + e^{-nix}}{2}</m>.</p>

      <p>Next, a little bit of wondrous math magic:
        <md>
          <mrow>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx \amp = \int -\frac{1}{64} \left((e^{6ix} + e^{-6ix}) - 6(e^{4ix} + e^{-4ix}) + 15(e^{2ix} + e^{-2ix}) - 20\right) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\frac{1}{32} \int \left(\frac{e^{6ix} + e^{-6ix}}{2} - 6\frac{e^{4ix} + e^{-4ix}}{2} + 15\frac{e^{2ix} + e^{-2ix}}{2} - 10\right) \: dx</mrow>
          <mrow>\amp = -\frac{1}{32} \int \cos(6x) - 6\cos(4x) + 15\cos(2x) - 10 \: dx</mrow>
        </md>
      </p>

      <p>All that's left to do is to integrate term by term to obtain the final result of<me>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx = -\frac{1}{192}\sin(6x) + \frac{3}{64}\sin(4x) - \frac{15}{64}\sin(2x) + \frac{5}{16}x + C.</me>I personally think that this is quite an elegant way of going about things, but your mileage may vary.</p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection xml-id="miscellaneous-three_methods-discussion">
      <title>"But what about larger <m>n</m>?"</title>

      <p>We have seen three ways of evaluating the integral<me>\int \sin^6(x) \: dx,</me>each with their own advantages and drawbacks. Notably, the first and third methods have final answers that look quite similar to each other, but the trig reduction formula returns a final function that is quite distinct from the other two.</p>

      <p>It's interesting to observe, for example, that the functions<me>-\frac{1}{6} \sin^{5}(x)\cos(x) - \frac{1}{24} \sin^{3}(x)\cos(x) - \frac{5}{16} \sin(x)\cos(x) + \frac{5}{16}x</me>and<me>-\frac{1}{192}\sin(6x) + \frac{3}{64}\sin(4x) - \frac{15}{64}\sin(2x) + \frac{5}{16}x</me> describe the same graph.</p>

      <p>We now discuss the relative efficiency of these three integration techniques for larger <m>n</m> in the integral<me>\int \sin^n(x) \: dx.</me>When <m>n</m> is quite large, the trig reduction method seems to be the fastest, most efficient method. There are patterns in the values of the coefficients which could be exploited to strategically reduce the amount of required calculations.</p>

      <p>Perhaps the most prominent downside to this technique is that the terms still contain powers of trigonometric functions, which might be undesirable.</p>

      <p>The next best method is, in my opinion, integration via complex trig definitions. As <m>n</m> increases, the bulk of the extra work is in the calculation of the binomial expansion and regrouping of terms. I do think this method beats the first one, though.</p>

      <p>Note that with the complex integration technique, we were able to express the integral in terms of trig functions without any squares, cubes, etc. If we needed to, say, integrate the integral of <m>\sin^6(x)</m>, it would be relatively quick and painless.</p>

      <p>As a challenge for the reader, you could try to evaluate <m>\int \sin^8(x) \: dx</m>? Or maybe something even crazier, like <m>\int \sin^{22}(x) \: dx</m>?</p>

      <p>Perhaps we've opened up too large a proverbial can of worms...</p>
    </subsection>
  </section>

</chapter>